Benjamin D. Killeen

Ph.D. Student, Johns Hopkins University Department of Computer Science 3400 N Charles St Baltimore, MD 21218, USA killeen@jhu.edu

💣 benjamindkilleen.com - 🚢 arcade.cs.jhu.edu - 🚢 cirl.lcsr.jhu.edu ➤ Benjamin D. Killeen - • 0000-0003-2511-7929 - • benjamindkilleen ♥ @bdkilleen - 🛅 benjamindkilleen - 🔟 @benjamindkilleen

Summary

A Ph.D. Student at Johns Hopkins University, I am interested in intelligent surgical systems that improve patient outcomes. My recent work involves realistic simulation of interventional X-ray imaging for the purpose of developing Al-integrated surgical systems. I am a member of the Advanced Robotics and Computationally Augmented Environments (ARCADE) research group and the Computational Interaction and Robotics Laboratory (CIRL).

Education

Ph.D., Computer Science, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA.	08/2019 - present
With Mathias Unberath and Gregory D. Hager.	
B.A., Computer Science with Honors, Minor in Physics , University of Chicago, Chicago, IL, USA.	09/2015 - 06/2019

Academic Experience

Research assistant , Department of Computer Science, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA. With Mathias Unberath, Gregory D. Hager.	08/2020 - present
Research Assistant, Laboratory for Computational Sensing and Robotics, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA. With Gregory D. Hager, Mathias Unberath, and Russel Taylor.	08/2019 - 06/2020
Research assistant , Department of Computer Science, University of Chicago, Chicago, IL, USA. With Gordon Kindlmann.	03/2018 - 08/2019

Professional Experience

Computer Vision / Al Intern , Applied Research, Intuitive Surgical Inc., Sunnyvale, CA, USA. With Omid Mohareri.	06/2020 - 07/2020
Software Development Intern, Cognitive Computing, Epic Systems, Verona, WI, USA. Research Intern, IBM Research - Almaden, San Jose, CA, USA. With Geoffrey Burr.	06/2018 - 08/2018 06/2017 - 08/2017

Selected Honors

Link Foundation Fellowship in Modeling, Simulation, and Training Proposal: Interactive Digital Twins for Simulating the Future of Work in Al- and Robot-assisted Operating Rooms	06/2023
Nominated, Intuitive/IPCAI Bench to Bedside Award For paper [J-5] at IPCAI 2023.	06/2023
Runner-up, Physics of Medical Imaging Best Student Paper Award For paper [C-5] at SPIE Medical Imaging 2022.	02/2022
Best Paper Award in Bioengineering For paper [C-4] at IEEE BIBE 2021.	10/2021
Best Presentation Award In Reliable Software Systems at Johns Hopkins University.	04/2021
Best Graduate Project Award In Computer Integrated Surgical Systems and Technology II at Johns Hopkins University.	05/2020
COVID 10 Detect Avend Vocale	04/2020

COVID-19 Dataset Award, Kaggle 04/2020 For the dataset in [M-1].

Intuitive Surgical Best Project Award.

12/2019

For Enriching Unsupervised Feature Learning via Intermediate Subtasks in Deep Learning at Johns Hopkins

LCSR Fellowship for Outstanding Incoming Ph.D. Students, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA. 2019 - 2020

Academic Services	President , LCSR Graduate Student Association at Johns Hopkins University. Established an executive board, annual operating budget, and election process.	08/2022 - present
	Sports Officer, MICCAI Society Student Board. Head of Student Resources, LCSR Graduate Student Committee at Johns Hopkins University.	12/2021 - present 09/2020 - 08/2022
Community	Family Member, Thread, Baltimore, MD, USA. Volunteer Instructor, CompileHer, Chicago, IL, USA.	06/2021 - 2022 2019
Peer Review	International Conference on Computer Vision (ICCV) Medical Imaging Computing and Computer Aided Interventions (MICCAI) Journal of Machine Learning Research (JMLR) IEEE Transactions on Medical Imaging (TMI) IEEE Robotics and Automation Letters (RA-L) International Symposium on Medical Robotics (ISMR) International Conference on Information Processing in Computer-Assisted Interventions (IPCAI)	2023
	MICCAI Educational Challenge Medical Image Analysis IEEE/CVF Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR)	2022
	IEEE/CVF Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR)	2021
	Nature Scientific Data	2020
Supervision		
Graduate Students	Han Zhang, Masters, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA.	01/2023 - present
	Aditya Kulkarni, Masters, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA.	09/2022 - present
	Qiyuan Wu , Masters, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA. Now an incoming PhD student at Cornell University.	08/2022 - present
	Zidi Tao , Research Assistant, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA. Now a PhD student at Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute.	10/2021 - 06/2022
	Shreya Chakraborty , Masters, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA. Now at PathAI.	08/2020 - 09/2021
	Philipp Nikutta , Visiting Masters, Technical University of Munich, Munich, Germany. Now at Argo Al.	12/2019 - 03/2020
Undergraduates	Sambhav Chordia, Bachelors, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA.	06/2022 - 12/2022
	Sean Sebastian Darcy, Bachelors, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA. Now an incoming PhD student at California Institute of Technology.	10/2021 - 10/2022
	Nethra Venkatayogi , Bachelors, The University of Texas at Austin, Austin, TX, USA. Now an incoming PhD student with Muyinatu Bell.	05/2021 - 10/2021
	Max Judish, Bachelors, Brown University, Providence, RI, USA.	01/2021 - 08/2021
Student Projects	Recreating Pelvic Trauma Surgery in Virtual Reality for the Development of Novel C-arm Interfaces Han Zhang, Zixuan Liu, Liam Wang. Computer Integrated Surgery II, Johns Hopkins Unviersity.	2023
	Real-time Integration of 2D-3D Pelvic Registration with Robotic X-ray Acquisition Jiaming Zhang, Zhangcong She. Computer Integrated Surgery II, Johns Hopkins Unviersity.	2023
	3D Segmentation of Hard and Soft Tissue for Simulating X-ray Image Formation with Deep Learning Qiyuan Wu, Zhiyuan Ding, Sean Darcy. Computer Integrated Surgery II, Johns Hopkins University.	2022
Assistant Teaching	Computer Integrated Surgery, Department of Computer Science, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA. With Russ Taylor. Wrote supplementary course material, led weekly office hours, and taught regular discussion sections.	Fall 2022
	Computer Integrated Surgery, Department of Computer Science, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA. With Russ Taylor and Emad Boctor.	Fall 2021
	Held weekly office hours and biweekly discussion sections. Managed grading together with Maia Stiber. Machine Learning and Large Scale Data Analysis, Department of Computer Science, University of Chicago, Chicago, IL, USA. With Yali Amit.	Spring 2019

Wrote supplementary course material and held weekly lab sessions. Graded coursework.

Selected review: "Ben was incredibly patient during office hours and always responsive to student questions. In addition, he often presented demos during office hours or showed easier ways to handle the homework assignments; both were very helpful."

More reviews available at benjamindkilleen.com/teaching/2019-spring-lsda

Teaching Services

Course assistant. Department of Computer Science, University of Chicago, Chicago, IL, USA

01/2019 - 08/2019

- Scientific Visualization
- Introduction to Computer Science I
- Introduction to Computer Science II

Tutoring in Computer Science, Machine Learning, Baltimore, MD, USA.

06/2020 - 08/2022

J-6

J-5

1-4

1-2

1_1

C-5

C-4

C-3

C - 1

M-3

M-2

M-1

Worked with middle and high school students.

Publications

I have first- (co-) authored 6 (4) peer-reviewed papers and 3 (0) preprints. My publication list is also available on Google Scholar. (*) denotes equal contribution.

Peer-reviewed Journal Articles

- **B.D. Killeen**, S.M. Cho, M. Armand, R.H. Taylor, M. Unberath. In Silico simulation: A key enabling technology for next-generation intelligent surgical systems. Progress in Biomedical Engineering, 2023. doi: 10.1088/2516-1091/acd28b.
- **B.D. Killeen**, C. Gao, K. Oguine, S. Darcy, M. Armand, R.H. Taylor, G. Osgood, M. Unberath. An Autonomous X-ray Image Acquisition and Interpretation System for Assisting Percutaneous Pelvic Fracture Fixation. To appear in International Journal of Computer Assisted Radiology and Surgery, 2023.
- Nominated for the Intuitive/IPCAI Bench to Bedside Award.
- C. Gao, **B.D. Killeen**, Y. Hu, R.B. Grupp, R.H. Taylor, M. Armand, M. Unberath. Synthetic data accelerates the development of generalizable learning-based algorithms for X-ray image analysis. Nature Machine Intelligence, Mar. 2023, pp. 1–15, doi: 10.1038/s42256-023-00629-1.
- **B. D. Killeen**, J. Winter, W. Gu, A. Martin-Gomez, R. H. Taylor, G. Osgood, M. Unberath. Mixed reality interfaces for achieving desired views with robotic X-ray systems. Computer Methods in Biomechanics and Biomedical Engineering: Imaging & Visualization, 7 Dec. 2022, pp. 1-6, doi: 10.1080/21681163.2022.2154272.
- Special issue: Augmented Environments for Computer Assisted Interventions (AE-CAI) 2022.
- A. Hundt, **B. Killeen**, H. Kwon, C. Paxton, GD Hager. "Good Robot!": Efficient Reinforcement Learning for Multi-Step Visual Tasks with Sim to Real Transfer. IEEE Robotics and Automation Letters, vol. 5, no. 4, pp. 6724–6731, Oct. 2020. doi: 10.1109/LRA.2020.3015448.
- S. Ambrogio, P. Narayanan, H. Tsai, R. M. Shelby, I. Boybat, C. di Nolfo, S. Sidler, M. Giordano, M. Bodini, N. Farinha, **B. Killeen**, C. Cheng, Y. Jaoudi, G. W. Burr. Equivalent-accuracy accelerated neural-network training using analogue memory. Nature, vol. 558, no. 7708, p. 60, Jun. 2018. doi: 10.1038/s41586-018-0180-5.

Peer-reviewed Conference Papers

- **B. D. Killeen**, Shreya Chakraborty, Greg Osgood, Mathias Unberath. Toward perception-based anticipation of cortical breach during K-wire fixation of the pelvis. Medical Imaging 2022: Physics of Medical Imaging. SPIE. doi: 10.1117/12.2612989.
- Runner-up, SPIE Medical Imaging Physics of Medical Imaging Best Student Paper Award
- J. D. Opfermann*, **B. D. Killeen***, C. Bailey, M. Khan, A. Uneri, K. Suzuki, M. Armand, F. Hui, A. Krieger**, M. Unberath**. Feasibility of a Cannula-mounted Piezo Robot for Image-guided Vertebral Augmentation: Toward a Low Cost, Semi-autonomous Approach. 2021 IEEE 21st International Conference on Bioinformatics and Bioengineering (BIBE), Kragujevac, Serbia, 2021 pp. 1-8. doi: 10.1109/BIBE52308.2021.9635356.
 *Joint first authors; ** joint last authors.
- Honored with Best Paper Award in Bioengineering.
- X. Liu*, **B. D. Killeen***, A. Sinha, M. Ishii, G. Hager, R. Taylor, M. Unberath. Neighborhood Normalization for Robust Geometric Feature Learning. Proceedings of the IEEE/CVF Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition, 2021.
- C. Gao, X. Liu, W. Gu, **B. D. Killeen**, M. Armand, R. Taylor, M. Unberath. Generalizing Spatial Transformers to Projective Geometry with Applications to 2D/3D Registrationc. MICCAI, 2020, arxiv:2003.10987.
- X. Liu, Y. Zhang, **B. Killeen**, M. Ishii, G. Hager, R. Taylor, M. Unberath. Extremely Dense Point Correspondences using a Learned Feature Descriptor. Proceedings of the IEEE/CVF Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition, pp. 4847-4856, 2020.

Preprints

- **B. D. Killeen**, H. Zhang, J. Mangulabnan, M. Armand, R.H. Taylor, G. Osgood, and M. Unberath, Pelphix: Surgical Phase Recognition from X-ray Images in Percutaneous Pelvic Fixation. arXiv preprint, 2023, arXiv:2304.09285
- J. Y. Wu*, **B. D. Killeen***, P. Nikutta, M. Thies, A. Zapaishchykova, S. Chakraborty, M. Unberath. Changes in Reproductive Rate of SARS-CoV-2 Due to Non-pharmaceutical Interventions in 1,417 U.S. Counties. medRxiv preprint, Jun. 2020, doi: 10.1101/2020.05.31.20118687.
- **B. D. Killeen***, J. Y. Wu*, K. Shah, A. Zapaishchykova, P. Nikutta, A. Tamhane, S. Chakraborty, J. Wei, T. Gao, M. Thies, M. Unberath. A County-level Dataset for Informing the United States' Response to COVID-19. arXiv preprint, 2020, arXiv:2004.00756.

Patents

G. W. Burr and **B. D. Killeen**. 2020. Efficient Processing of Convolutional Neural Network Layers Using Analog-memory-based Hardware. 20200117986, filed March 25, 2019, and issued April 16, 2020, uspto.report/patent/app/20200117986.

P-1

Selected Press

Graham, Catherine. "Synthetic Data for Al Outperform Real Data in Robot-Assisted Surgery." The Johns

Hopkins University Hub. The Johns Hopkins University, March 20, 2023. hub.jhu.edu/2023/03/20/syntheticdata-outperform-real-data-robot-assisted-surgery/.

Dziarkach, Andrei. "Details with Andrei Dziarkach." Voice of America. November 21, 2020 Accessed

November 26, 2020. golosameriki.com/a/detali/5671254.html.

Rosen, Jill. "Dog Training Methods Help JHU Teach Robots to Learn New Tricks." The Johns Hopkins University Hub. The Johns Hopkins University, October 26, 2020. hub.jhu.edu/2020/10/26/positive-

reinforcement-for-robots

Selected Coursework

Graduate Vision as Bayesian Inference

Reliable Software Systems Theory of Computation Parallel Programming Nonlinear Optimization II Computer Integrated Surgery II Computer Integrated Surgery I

Deep Learning

Undergraduate Unsupervised Learning*

Computer Vision

Machine Learning and Large Scale Data Analysis

Operating Systems Honors Combinatorics Honors Algorithms

Honors Discrete Mathematics Scientific Visualization Programming Languages Networks and Distributed Systems

Quantum Mechanics I \& II Intermediate Mechanics

Electronics Wizards

*Graduate level.

Memberships International Society for Optics and Photonics (SPIE) Student Member

Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers (IEEE) Graduate Student Member

Extracurricular In my free time, I enjoy bouldering, cycling, and running. I am an avid fan of art museums, and I write

Creative nonfiction: benjamindkilleen.com/blog

Science fiction.

This document is available Metadata

- online: benjamindkilleen.com/markdown-cv.

- as a PDF: benjamindkilleen.com/files/cv.pdf.

Created based on markdown-cv by Eliseo Papa with styles based on David Whipp.

MIT License.

Last updated: May 2023

2023

2020

GPA: 3.82

GPA: 3.81